Guide to the Bhatt Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Bhatt family papers
1941-1988
MS 1705
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.79
(4 boxes)
The collection includes correspondence and other materials, primarily written by Nanabhai K. Bhatt to his son Pravin N. Bhatt. The materials document the political and social climate in India from the late 1940s through the early 1960s. In addition, collection materials provide background information on Pravin Bhatt's career as a scientist at Yale University and internationally.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Pravin N. Bhatt, 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Separated Materials
Approximately 34 publications (books, pamphlets, and magazines) were removed from the Bhatt Family Papers and given to the Southeast Asia Collection curator in the Yale University Library.
Associated Materials
Pancholi Collection of Gandhi Letters (MS 1483). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Biographical / Historical
Nanabhai K. Bhatt was an Indian educator and colleague of Mahatma Gandhi. Dr. Pravin Bhatt, his son, is a researcher at the Yale School of Medicine.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes correspondence and other materials, primarily written by Nanabhai K. Bhatt to his son Pravin N. Bhatt. The materials document the political and social climate in India from the late 1940s through the early 1960s. In addition, collection materials provide background information on Pravin Bhatt's career as a scientist at Yale University and internationally.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by type of material.
India -- Politics and government; India -- Social life and customs; Bhaṭṭa, Nānābhāī, 1882-1961; Bhaṭṭa, Pravīna Nā. (Pravīṇa Nānābhāī); Gandhi, Mahatma, 1869-1948
- Correspondence
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence, unless otherwise noted, is from Nanabhai K. Bhatt to his son Pravin N. Bhatt and family. It frequently includes information about general family matters, including celebrations, traditions, travel, and health issues.
  - 1941-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
  - From Pancholi family to Pravin N. Bhatt, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - From Nanabhai K. Bhatt to Haribhai Pathak, father of Indu Bhatt, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Nanabhai Bhatt wrote these letters from prison following his arrest by the British authorities for pro-Indian activities.
  - From Nanabhai K. Bhatt to his sons Pravin and Batuk, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Written while Nanabhai Bhatt was in prison following his arrest by the British authorities for his pro-Indian political activities. His family did not know where he was for a month following his arrest.
  - From Nanabhai K. Bhatt to Haribhai Pathak and Indu Bhatt, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - From Sarabhai family to Pravin N. Bhatt, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - From Pandit Sukhalalji to Nanabhai K. Bhatt, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - From Nanabhai K. Bhatt to Indu Bhatt, his daughter-in-law, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - From Nanabhai K. Bhatt to Pravin and Indu Bhatt and others in Calcutta, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Pravin Bhatt was studying at the School of Tropical Medicine in Calcutta at the time, and became ill.
  - 1949 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
    Includes letter in English to Secretary of Health for the Indian government.
  - 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1950 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1952 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    To Indu Bhatt and friends about going to the United States and to Pravin Bhatt about his wife joining him in the U.S.
  - From Jivraj Mehta to Pravin Bhatt regarding job difficulties and from Nanabhai K. Bhatt to Pravin and Indu Bhatt regarding their return to the United States, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1955 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Some letters written from Delhi, where Nanabhai Bhatt served as a member of the upper house of the Indian Parliament. Documents discussions with high-level government officials regarding potential jobs for Pravin Bhatt that might utilize his medical training in the U.S and possible living arrangements in Mumbai.
  - 1956 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Letters document Nanabhai Bhatt's work in Delhi and at the Lok Bharati (People's College), and his various travels.
  - 1957 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Includes details concerning a visit to the house of Swami Anand, a follower of Gandhi, near Bombay. Also includes information about attendance at UNESCO conference.
  - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1959 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Some correspondence relates to Pravin Bhatt's trip to Russia for research consultations.
  - 1960 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - To Pravin N. Bhatt from Manubhai Pancholi, 1942-1968 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Correspondence concerns political and social topics of the day. Pancholi, a protege of Gandhi's, taught at Lok Bharati.
  - To Pravin N. Bhatt, condolences on the death of his father, Nanabhai K. Bhatt, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    In English.
  - To Pravin N. Bhatt from Swami Anand, 1960-1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes correspondence on Bhatt's brother's sudden death while working in labor relations in an Indian textile factory.
  - Pravin N. Bhatt, "Report of European Tour," typescript, 1958 September-October (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1952-1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Passports and passport photograph, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Yale University Biological Safety Advisory Committee, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Clippings and notes regarding Pravin Bhatt's time at Tulane University, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Awards, 1954-1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Griffin Award (American Association of Laboratory Animal Science), 1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Slides and photographs of Lok Bharati, high school for Indian teenagers, Circa 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  Nanabhai Bhatt was the founder of Lok Bharati (People's College).
- Slides of Gandhi, including the salt march, Before 1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Slides were given to Pravin Bhatt and were produced in circa 1970s.
- Mr. Pancholi's lecture at Yale on the donation of the Gandhi letters, 1988 October 29; 1 audiocassette (Box 3)
  Lecture is in English.
- Gandhi's salt march in 1928, Circa 1970-1979; 1 (Box 4)
  Original compilation of film clips, in chronological order, documenting the salt march. Compiled by Mohan Parikh, not commercially produced.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - Use copy, 1 (Box 4U)